Guide to the American Social Science Association Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Social Science Association Records
1863-1906
1865-1887
MS 1603
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
(13 boxes)
The records include organizational papers, minutes, correspondence, financial records, and committee files which document the founding of the American Social Science Association in 1865 and its functioning over the next twenty-five years. The records highlight the work of Franklin Benjamin Sanborn as secretary of the association. The records also include files of the Conference of Charities and Corrections which met with the American Social Science Association.
American Social Science Association
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale Law School, 1989.
Scope and Contents
The American Social Science Association Records consist of organizational papers, minutes, correspondence, financial records, and committee files, which document the history of the American Social Science Association from its founding in 1865 through the first twenty-five years of its existence. The files are an incomplete record of the period but highlight the work of Franklin Benjamin Sanborn as secretary of the association and active member of many committees. The records also include files relating to other social science organizations, in which Sanborn was active. The most numerous of these files is for the Conference of Charities and Corrections.
The Manuscripts and Archives Department received the records from the Yale University Law School in 1989, after Morris Cohen, the Yale Law Librarian, found them in a trunk in the Law School basement. How the records came to be in the Law School's keeping is not entirely clear. It appears that at its demise at least some of the ASSA library was deposited in the Yale Law School. It is possible that Simeon E. Baldwin, who had for some years been a leader of the association, played some role in this deposit. The records of the association came as part of the library, but unlike the printed volumes in the library, the records were left uncatalogued.
Biographical / Historical
The American Social Science Association (ASSA) was founded in Boston in 1865. Through a letter circulated by the Massachusetts Board of Charities, prominent social reformers and intellectuals were asked to form an American organization, similar to the British Social Science Association, to understand and improve a rapidly changing society. As the circular explained, the society would discuss "those questions relating to the Sanitary Condition of the people, the Relief, Employment and Education of the Poor, the Prevention of Crime, the Amelioration of the Criminal Law, the Discipline of Prisons, the Remedial Treatment of the Insane, and those numerous matters of statistical and philanthropic interest which are included under the general head of 'social science.'" At its first meeting the association adopted a constitution and elected William Barton Rogers as president. Franklin Benjamin Sanborn served as secretary.
The association structured itself in four departments: Education; Public Health; Jurisprudence; and Economy, Trade and Finance. The latter department would later be split into the Department of Social Economy and the Finance Department. The leadership of the departments was built on existing professional specializations; doctors chaired Health, lawyers led Jurisprudence, and college professors took charge of Education.
The association expected its members, professionals along with humanitarian reformers and businessmen, "to collect all facts, diffuse all knowledge, and stimulate all inquiry, which have a bearing on social welfare." Members were to meet together regularly to read papers and discuss social economics and the means to human improvement. Members presented their papers at large general meetings; the association published several of these papers; and meetings received detailed coverage in the local press.
In 1868 the association's executive committee appointed Henry Villard as permanent secretary. In 1870 Villard resigned from the post, leaving the association with no permanent secretary and consequently no effective leadership. The association even discussed disbanding. Then in October, 1873, the board named Sanborn permanent secretary and the association began to revive. Under Sanborn, the ASSA forged a link with the National Conference of Charities and Corrections (NCCC), and the two organizations continued to meet together for a decade.
The very broad base membership of the ASSA led to tensions which would eventually split the association. The delegates to the NCCC were interested in practical solutions to the problems of the poor, the insane, and the criminal classes. They found the papers presented by academics within the ASSA to be too theoretical and abstract. At one time the ASSA executive committee discussed a plan to merge the association with Johns Hopkins University, by which academic inquirers would gain a viable framework for organizing their disciplines. This plan did not gain approval, and in the meantime academic specialists began to form their own associations in their fields of social science. The American Historical Association was formed in 1884; they met with the ASSA but refused to organize as a subordinate department in the ASSA. In 1885 economists formed the American Economic Association followed in 1903 by the American Political Science Association and in 1905 by the American Sociological Society.
After a period of comparative financial security in the 1880s, the association faced financial hard times in the 1890s. Its members were drifting to other more specialized organizations and its role or purpose was not clear. By 1908 the association was unable to marshal the strength to hold its annual meeting.
The association is the subject of Thomas L. Haskell's monograph The Emergence of Professional Social Science: the American Social Science Association and the Nineteenth-Century Crisis of Authority. Those desiring a more detailed history of the ASSA should refer to this volume (University of Illinois Press, Urbana, Illinois, 1977).
Arrangement
The records are arranged in two series: Series I. Association records, 1863-1906. Series II. Related associations records, 1865-1889.
Series I includes the records of the American Social Science Association, while Series II is composed of material of other social science organizations. Materials in both series appear to have been in the possession of Franklin Benjamin Sanborn. Materials in Series I seem to have come into Sanborn's care, when he was secretary of the ASSA. One cannot be certain that materials in Series II have any relation to the ASSA material in Series I. In the case of the National Conference of Charities and Corrections there is an obvious link between it and the ASSA. For any other organization there may be no other connection than the fact that Franklin Benjamin Sanborn was active in it.
Public welfare; Social sciences -- United States -- History; Barnard, James M. (James Munson), 1819-1904; Bradford, Gamaliel, 1831-1911; Lincoln, David F. (David Francis), 1841-1916; Sanborn, F. B. (Franklin Benjamin), 1831-1917; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910; Villard, Henry, 1835-1900; Wayland, Francis, 1826-1904; Wells, David A. (David Ames), 1828-1898; American Social Science Association; Boston Social Science Association; Conference of Charities and Correction (U.S.)
- Association records, 1863-1906; Series I; 4.75' (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I begins with surviving records of the ASSA's annual and general meetings. This arrangement places records of the first annual meeting, including the invitation to meet, response to the invitation, proceedings, and clippings from the founding meeting at the very beginning of the records. For other meetings, the files in the series may include copies of papers read at meetings, correspondence relating to arrangements for the meeting, and newspaper clippings describing the proceedings.
  General correspondence follows the records of meetings. Most letters are incoming and are from members, as well as public school, prison and health administrators, state legislators, and other city and state officers. The letters are, for the most part, addressed to the association secretary but are occasionally addressed to other ASSA officers. The letters include responses to invitations to join the ASSA or to provide a paper for a meeting, requests for ASSA literature, orders for proceedings, or reactions to organizational policies. Since the association solicited members from such a broad base, the files contain letters from some of the most prominent individuals of the age including at least single letters from Lyman Abbott, Henry Adams, C. Loring Brace, Charles W. Eliot, George Washington Cable, Melville Dewey, E. M. Gallaudet, James A. Garfield, Daniel Coit Gilman, E. L. Godkin, Washington Gladden, Rutherford B. Hays, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Julia Ward Howe, Frederick Law Olmstead, Josiah Quincy, Theodore Roosevelt, Carl Schurz, Lewis Tappan, and Frances Willard.
  The earliest correspondence (1865-1869) is arranged alphabetically in file folders by correspondent name. For the period 1870-1871, there are incomplete letterbooks of alphabetically arranged incoming letters, in addition to one folder of loose correspondence. There is also a letterbook containing copies of outgoing letters in chronological order for 1869-1870.
  The remainder of the general correspondence is unbound and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent name. Most incoming letters are addressed to Sanborn. Though this correspondence spans the period 1873-1885, it is fragmentary. There are, for instance, few letters from 1875, and the period from 1880-1884 is not documented. Correspondents represented in the records by five or more letters are listed in the finding aid. These correspondents are normally active association members and officers such as James Barnard, Gamaliel Bradford, David Francis Lincoln, Henry Villard, David Wells, and Francis Wayland.
  The general correspondence is followed by records of various officers. In this section are found minutes of executive committee meetings; the secretary's reports and papers; treasurer's records, including correspondence on membership and financial matters, accounts and vouchers, and lists of members and journal subscribers; and librarian's records consisting of lists of library holdings and records of the library's transfer to the Yale Law School.
  The series includes some records from each of the ASSA's individual departments. These records include correspondence relating to a department's work, minutes of meetings, annual reports, and topical files containing clippings and research material on subjects studied by the department. The records of the Health Department also include entries for an essay contest sponsored by the department. At the end of the series there are two folders containing publications of the ASSA.
  The records in this series are arranged in five sections: Annual/general meetings; General correspondence; Officers' records; Departmental records; and Publications.
  - Annual/general meetings
    - First annual and general meetings, Boston
      - Invitation to meet and responses, 1865 August-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Proceedings and other documents relating to the founding of the association, 1865 September-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
        General note
        See also: box 7, folder 181
      - Clippings, 1865 September-October (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Second general meeting, Boston, 1865 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Second annual and third general meeting, New Haven, 1866 October
      - Minutes, clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Papers presented (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Third annual meeting, Boston, 1867 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fifth general meeting, New York, 1867 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fourth annual meeting, Boston, 1868 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Special meeting, New York: civil service reform, 1869 January (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General meeting, Albany, 1869 February (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Eighth general meeting, New York, 1869 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ninth general meeting, Philadelphia, 1870 October (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Annual meeting (adjourned), Boston, 1872 November (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - General meeting, Boston (also known as the "Eighth general meeting"), 1873 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - General meeting, New York, 1874 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Meeting in Detroit, 1875 May (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Meeting in Boston, 1875 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Annual meeting, Boston, 1876 January (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - General meeting, Saratoga, 1876 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Annual meeting, Boston, 1877 January (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - General meeting, Saratoga
      - Correspondence, 1877 September (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Clippings, 1877 September (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Papers read, 1877 September (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Annual meeting, Boston, 1878 January (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified meetings: clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General correspondence
    - A-G, 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - H-O, 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - P-S, 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - T-W, 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Letterpress copybook, 1869-1870 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Letterbook: A-H, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Letterbook: I-P, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Letterbook: M-Z, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - A-Z, 1870-1871 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - A-Am, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - An-Ay, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - A. Williams and Co., 1876-1879 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - American Historical Association, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Anderson, Martin B., 1876-1877, 1885, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Angell, George T., 1874-1879, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Atkinson, Edward, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Ba-Bl, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Bo-Bu, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Baker, Henry B., 1873-1878 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Balch, Thomas, 1876, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Barnard, James M., 1874, 1876, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
      See also: box 9, folder 207
    - Blatchford, J. S., 1873-1879 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Brace, C. L., 1874, 1878, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Brackett, Anna C., 1874 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Brainerd, Cephas, 1874 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Brockway, Z. R., 1873-1876 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Ca-Chi, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Chu-Cu, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Carroll, Alfred L., 1874, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Coffin, Charles F., 1874-1878 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Cotting, B. E., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Curtis, George William, 1874-1876, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - D, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Dall, Caroline H., 1876-1880, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Delafield, Lewis L., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Dwight, Theodore W., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - E, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Eaton, Derman B., 1873-1874, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Eaton, John, 1876, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Eliot, Charles W., 1874, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Eliot, Samuel, 1878, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - F, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Flagg, W. C., 1874, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Forbes, R. B., 1874, 1879, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Ga-Go, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Gr-Gu, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1877-1878, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Gallaudet, E. M., 1874 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Gano, John A., 1877-1878 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Garfield, James A., 1874 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Gilman, D. C., 1874-1879, 1885, undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Godkin, E. L., 1874, 1878, undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Greenough, W. W., 1874, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Ha, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - He-Ho, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Hu-Hy, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Hale, Edward E., 1874-1879, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Hamilton, Peter, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Hammond, William G., 1874-1877, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Harris, D. L., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Harris, Elisha, 1874-1876, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Harris, William T., 1874-1878, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Hill, Hamilton A., 1874-1878 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Hitchcock, Henry, 1876, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Holmes, Oliver W., Jr., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Horton, S. Dana, 1876, 1878, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Houghton and Co., 1874-1878 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Howells, W. D., 1874 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Hoyt, John W., 1874-1879 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Hubbard, Gardiner G., 1874, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Hunt, Ezra M., 1878-1879, undated (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - I, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - J, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Jenkins, J. Foster, 1874, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Jüngst, W., 1876 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - K, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Kimball, W. H., 1874, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - King, Rufus, 1878, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - L, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Lea, Henry C., 1874-1879 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Letchworth, William B., 1874, 1878, 1885-1886 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Lincoln, D. F. See also: Department of Health, 1873-1879, undated (Box 5, Folder 109-110)
    - Lodge, Anna Cabot, 1874, 1885, undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Logan, Thomas M., 1874, 1877 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Lynde, M. E. P., 1874-1878, undated (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Ma-Mic, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Mil-Mu, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Maris, George C., 1876 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Matile, George A., 1876-1877 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - May, Abby W., 1876, undated (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Meade, E. R., 1877 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Myers, Sydney, 1875-1877 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - N-New, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Newe-No, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - National Prison Association
      See: box 7, folder 173
    - New York Free Trade Club, 1877, undated (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Nourse, B. F., 1876-1877 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - O, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Olmstead, Frederick Law, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Pa-Pe, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Pf-Pu, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Peabody Institute, 1874, 1877 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Peirce, Benjamin, 1876, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Penn Monthly, 1874, 1877, undated (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Philadelphia Social Science Association, 1874-1878, undated (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - Porter, Robert P., 1877 (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Potter, Elisha R., 1874, undated (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Quincy, Josiah, 1873-1874, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Ra-Ri, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Ro-Ry, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Rand, Avery and Co., Printers, 1876-1877 (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Robert Clarke and Co., 1876-1878 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Rogers, William B., 1874-1877 (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, 1877, 18798 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Ruffner, W. H., 1876-1879 (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Sa-Sh, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Si-Su, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Schuyler, Louisa Lee, 1874-1875 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1874-1878 (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Snow, Edwin M., 1874-1876 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Sowdon, A. J. C., 1877, undated (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1878-1879, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Sumner, William Graham, 1874-1877, undated (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Ta-Th, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - Ti-Ty, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - Thayer, James B., 1874-1879 (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - Townsend, J. P., 1876-1879 (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - U, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - V, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - Villard, Henry, 1877-1879 (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - Wa-Wee, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Wel-Wi, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Wo-Wr, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Walker, Francis A., 1876-1877 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Ward, Henry Galbraith
      See: box 6, folder 132
    - Waring, George E., Jr., 1876-1880 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Washburn, Emory, 1874, 1876 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Wayland, Francis, 1876-1879, 1885, undated (Box 6, Folder 164-165)
    - Wells, David A., 1874-1877, undated (Box 7, Folder 166-167)
    - White, Andrew D., 1874-1879, 1885 (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - White, Horace, 1876-1879, 1885 (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Whitman, S. W., 1874, undated (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Wigglesworth, Edward, Jr., 1874-1879, undated (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - Wilbur, H. B., 1876-1877, undated (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Wines, E. C., 1873-1877 (Box 7, Folder 173)
    - Woolsey, Theodore D., 1874-1877 (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - Wrigley, E., 1875-1879 (Box 7, Folder 175)
    - Y, Circa 1873-1885 (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Unidentified, fragments, 1876-1880, undated (Box 7, Folder 177)
  - Officers' records
    - Executive committee
      - Minutes, 1867-1873 (Box 7, Folder 178)
      - Minutes, clippings, 1875-1880, 1885, undted (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - Board of Directors' Committee of Five: minutes, 1873 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Secretary's records
      - Recording secretary's book: constitution, minutes of public meetings, minutes of executive committee meetings, 1865 September-December (Box 7, Folder 181)
      - Records of constitutional revision, 1872 (Box 7, Folder 182)
      - Secretary's reports, 1868-1870, 1875-1879, undated (Box 8, Folder 183-185)
    - Treasurer's records
      - Correspondence, general, 1871-1878, undated (Box 8, Folder 186)
      - Correspondence re membership and publications, 1874-1879, 1887, undated (Box 8, Folder 187-196)
      - Balance sheets, 1865-1870, undated (Box 8, Folder 197-198)
      - Expenditures, 1865-1870, February (Box 8, Folder 199-200)
      - Expenditures: cancelled checks and checkbook, 1869-1870 (Box 9, Folder 201)
      - Expenditures, 1870March-1876, undated (Box 9, Folder 202)
      - List of members and annual subscriptions, 1869-1876 (Box 9, Folder 203)
      - List of journal subscribers, 1870, undated (Box 9, Folder 204)
      - Receipts, 1869, 1873, undated (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - Librarian's records
      - Department of Health: library holdings, [1867] (Box 9, Folder 206)
      - Department of Jurisprudence: library holdings, [1867] (Box 9, Folder 207)
      - Department of Social Economy: library holdings, [1867] (Box 10, Folder 208)
      - Miscellaneous records, 1870-1871, 1877 (Box 10, Folder 209)
      - Records of library's transfer to Yale Law School, 1906, undated (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Departmental records
    - Education
      - General committee records, 1869-1874, undated (Box 10, Folder 211)
      - Committee on Art in Education, 1869-1870, undated (Box 10, Folder 212)
      - Public meetings, 1867, undted (Box 10, Folder 213)
      - Topical file: education, general, 1870, undated (Box 10, Folder 214)
      - Topical file: reformatories, reform schools, and asylums for children, 1866, 1870, undated (Box 10, Folder 215)
      - Topical file: social science instruction, 1866 (Box 10, Folder 216)
    - Finance, 1867 (Box 10, Folder 217)
    - Health
      - General Committee: minutes and associated documents, 1869 April-1871 Jan, 1873, undated (Box 10, Folder 218)
      - Annual reports, 1870, 1876-1878 (Box 10, Folder 219)